<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Security | Sainsmograf]]></title>
  <link href="http://arifwn.github.io/blog/categories/security/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://arifwn.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-17T13:20:19+07:00</updated>
  <id>http://arifwn.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Arif Widi Nugroho]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cryptography Primer]]></title>
    <link href="http://arifwn.github.io/blog/2013/07/15/encryption-primer/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-15T20:37:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>http://arifwn.github.io/blog/2013/07/15/encryption-primer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The uproar caused by recent leak from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Snowden">Edward Snowden</a> still hasn&rsquo;t receded yet. There are various stances about privacy and government snooping floating around in the internet. Some say they have <a href="https://twitter.com/_nothingtohide">nothing to hide</a>. Others argue if the government can snoop you, and black-hat hackers can snoop the government, then we&rsquo;re royally screwed because anybody with money can pay the black-hats (or, gasp!, pay some corrupt government officials) to get data about anybody.</p>

<p>Politics aside, security must be taken seriously every time we use internet. In this post I would like to talk about the basic of security in general computing today.</p>

<h2>Basic Cryptography</h2>

<p>In general, cryptography is used to transform a string of text into a convoluted mumbo-jumbo that do not have any resemblance to the original text whatsoever to a person without access to its encryption key. That original string of text is called plaintext, and the resulting mumbo-jumbo is called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ciphertext">cyphertext</a>.</p>

<p>Based on the keys used for the encryption, there are two type of encryption: symmetric-key and asymmetric-key encryption.</p>

<p>In symmetric-key encryption, the key that uses to encrypt the plaintext into cyphertext can be used to reverse the operation. Decrypting the resulting cyphertext using the same key will yield the same plain text. So, if two people can share an encryption key, they can communicate securely using that key. A simple example is sharing an encrypted rar file with your partner, your partner must know your encryption key (the password) in order to decrypt the rar file. So, you can go meet your partner and tell him your password.</p>

<p>What if it&rsquo;s impossible for you to meet your partner physically?  Supposedly, the secrecy of the data you want to transmit is very important and the balance of the world would be disrupted if it compromised. How can you tell him your password with a strong guarantee that nobody snoop it in between the transit? Using email? Email is generally transmitted in plain text, anybody in the network between you and your partner can read it. Using google chat? Then google can read it whenever it please. Using text message? Then the cellphone operator can read it. Also, <a href="http://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2010/12/15-phone-3-minutes-all-thats-needed-to-eavesdrop-on-gsm-call/">gsm security is considered broken</a> and anyone with the right equipment can intercept your message. It&rsquo;s time to use an asymmetric-key encryption.</p>

<p>In asymmetric-key encryption, you have two keys instead of one: the private keys (which you should guard with your life) and the public key (which you should share to anyone and their pets). So, why does it require two keys?</p>

<p>Anybody who know your public key can encrypt a plaintext that only you can decrypt (using your private key). Consider our example above (in which you need to transmit a super secret data to your partner). You can encrypt the password with your partner&rsquo;s public key, and send him the resulting cyphertext. Using his private key, he&rsquo;ll decrypt the cyphertext and get the password. Then you can send him your password protected rar archive to him.</p>

<p>Wait, why use rar? Why not simply encrypt the data using the public key instead?</p>

<p>Well, actually you can use anything that properly encrypt the data. <a href="http://www.7-zip.org/">7-zip</a> support AES encryption (one of the commonly used symmetric-key encryption) too, just like rar. The reason why we didn&rsquo;t encrypt the whole data (presumably we have 1.3GB of it for the example) using the asymmetric-key encryption is it&rsquo;s really slow compared to the symmetric-key encryption. It is much more efficient (and faster) to encrypt the data using symmetric-key encryption and send the key/password through asymmetric-key encryption instead of encrypting the data wholesale using asymmetric-key encryption. Over time, the latest advances in cryptography will make the asymmetric-key encryption as fast as the symmetric-key encryption.</p>

<h2>Can We Break The Encryption?</h2>

<p>Cryptography relies heavily on random number. For example, you don&rsquo;t want your keys to be easily guessable by anyone, you want it sufficiently random that the odds of guessing your so low nobody want to even try to guess it (that&rsquo;s why you should favor randomly generated key over simple memorable string).</p>

<p>But how do we obtain a truly random number from inside a computer? A computer by itself cannot generate a truly random number. A computer is a state machine, so in theory, if you know the machine state at the time the secret random number generated, you might be able to guess that number. So we need another source of randomness to feed the random number generator so it can spit out numbers with more randomness. That source of randomness could be a network interface, human input, or even <a href="http://phys.org/news1147.html">cosmic rays</a>.</p>

<p>Starting from the Ivy Bridge processors, Intel includes an on-chip random number generator along with a new instruction to make uses of it, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RDRAND">RDRAND</a>. It can generate a random bit for each clock cycle. Modern operating systems use the instruction as additional source of randomness for their built-in random number generator.</p>

<p>There are <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=6038473">concerns regarding the use of RDRAND in linux kernel</a>. Since RDRAND uses an on-chip random number generator, somebody at processor manufacturing plant could replace the chip with the one with faulty random number generator, which would potentially compromise security on linux system.</p>

<p>Should we worry that an exploit to random number generator could compromise our security? Probably not, but keep it in mind though.</p>

<p>Break time. I&rsquo;ll continue later (stay tuned)&hellip;</p>

<p>Next:</p>

<ul>
<li>Quantum computing: can it break our decades-long asymmetric-key encryption?</li>
</ul>


<h2>Securing Email</h2>

<p>Emails are generally transmitted as plain-text. However, there are many ways to secure them. The question is, can it be done easily?</p>

<h2>Verifying Website Security</h2>

<p>Is the website you visit frequently actually secure? Are you sure the website you visit is actually the real website, not some hacker rig impersonating the real website?</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.eff.org/pages/tor-and-https">EFF has a nice diagram about connection privacy</a>. Lets discuss it!</li>
<li>Anything without HTTPS is insecure. Don&rsquo;t submit important information over plain http!</li>
</ul>


<h2>How SSL (HTTPS) Works</h2>

<ul>
<li>Initial handshake uses asymmetric encryption to exchange symmetric keys. Therefore HTTPS requires two roundtrip to server. SPDY protocol solve this (but chrome-only).</li>
<li>Validation: The connection might be encrypted, but how can you be sure that the guys on the other side of the cable are not an imposter? Someone I trusted should confirm that I&rsquo;m indeed not talking to a fake imposter.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Deep Net</h2>

<ul>
<li>We need to go <a href="https://www.torproject.org/">deeper</a>.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
